M Usman Maqbool **Bhutta**

Robotics Institute, CYT Building, HKUST, Clear Water Bay, HK

□ (+852) 609-44-786 | wsmanmaqbool@outlook.com | # usmanmaqbool.github.io | □ UsmanMaqbool | □ usmanmaqbool

"Be so good they can't ignore you."

Summary.

With the rise of autonomous systems, being a researcher and entrepreneur, my research direction is their deployment to the real world. For any autonomous mode of the robot, a 3D map is essential to navigate and operate at any place. I work to tackle the problems related to scale difference and loop closures for large scale 3D mapping. I've 7+ years of experience specializing in robotics R&D and project management. I previously owned an IT company, and I've been part of several startups since 2011. My full profile can view here (https://usmanmaqbool.github.io/).

Work Experience [7+ Years]

RESEARCH (COMPUTER VISION TECHNOLOGIES AND ROBOTICS SYSTEM)

Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, Robotics Institute

HKUST, HK

PHD CANDIDATE

Sep 2016 - Present

- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- Research in Place Recognition In-Progress: I'm currently working for making the better place recognition for the robotic state estimation by better scene understanding compared to the relocalization technologies. This work evaluation is done on the Pittsburge and Tokyo 247 Datasets compared to NetVLAD and APANet.

Development Using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Research in Multi-Agent SLAM: I've produced Loop-box for the multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large scale semi dense 3D reconstruction /large-scale structure from motion. This work got accepted in IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics..

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, UGV, LSD-SLAM, Monocular Camera.

Research in SLAM: I've worked mainly for the multi-agent SLAM system. To find the scale difference and excellent relative transformation between difference agents. I've produced PCR-Pro work. This work got best student paper finalist award at IEEE-CYBER 2018.

Development using: C++ 11, ROS, OpenCV, OpenGV, Paraview, EVO, Monocular Camera, Plotly

• Research in Automation: For smartphone glass inspection, I've introduced Smart-Inspect work. This work is accepted in IROS 2020. The patent is also under-review in the US.

Development using: Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, K-Means, Docker, Machine learning (ML)

Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL)

ETH Zürich, Switzerland.

ACADEMIC GUEST

Oct. 2019 - Mar. 2020

- Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Research in Place Recognition: I've worked for making the better place recognition for the better scene understanding. Furthermore, I've also introduced light weight representation of key-frames for better channel utilization.

Development using: MATLAB, Python, Jupyter, Nvidia CUDA, Docker, Deep learning, Matconvnet

Department of Electronics

QAU, Pakistan

MPHIL CANDIDATE

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- M.Phil. Supervisor: **Prof Hasan Mahmood**, Department of Electronics, QAU.
- Research in Image Processing (CNN): I've introduced CNN-based license plate recognition of Pakistani's Cars. This work has been published in IEEE-ICALIP 2014.

INDUSTRY AND ENTREPRENEURSHIP

Lisee Technology Corporation Limited

Central, HK

Jan 2018 - Present

- Won funding support for company | TSSSU Support HK\$ 300,000 (Jun 19 May 20).
- Indoor Navigation for Libray using Lisee Technology | PCF Support HK\$ 160,000 (Jun 18 May 19).

Friends Corporate Technologies

Islamabad, PK

Feb 2013 - Aug 2015

50+ Projects | Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing, Web Applications Development, MVC Applications

Federal Government of Pakistan

Islamabad, PK May 2012 - Feb 2013

SCIENTIFIC OFFICER

1

Electronics/ Electrical Engineering, R&D, image processing Server4Sale, LLC

Islamabad, PK Dec 2009 - Mar 2010

PHP DEVELOPER

Php web application development for Joomla and Zend frameworks.

DECEMBER 31, 2020 BHUTTA, M USMAN MAQBOOL · CURRICULUM VITAE

ACADEMIC

Department of Computer Science

BZU-Sahiwal, Pakistan

Feb 2016 - Jun 2016

Oct. 2015 - May. 2016

LECTURER (VISITING)

Teaching MCS and BS-CS courses

Department of Physics

GPGC Sahiwal, Pakistan

CTI

Teaching BS physics (Electronics related courses + Labs + Projects)

Department of Electronics

QAU, Pakistan

INSTRUCTER Aug. 2010 - Dec. 2010

'PHP Web Development' (a short course) offered in Department of Electronics, Quaid-i-Azam University, Islamabad, Pakistan.

Education

Ph.D. Candidate in Robotics at RAM-LAB, Robotics Institute

HKUST, Hong Kong

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONIC & COMPUTER ENGINEERING, THE HONG KONG UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY

Sep. 2016 - ~Feb. 2021

- PhD Supervisor: Prof Ming Liu, Director of Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab (RAM-LAB)
- Exchange Supervisor: Prof. Roland Siegwart, Director of Autonomous Systems Lab (ASL), ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Exchange Co-Supervisor: Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma, Senior Researcher at ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland.
- Got PEEF CCMS PhD scholarship from Pakistan and overseas research award (ORA).
- Research: Multi-Agent SLAM System, Place Recognition, Autonomous Car and Deep Learning for automation industry. Hand on experience on RGB-D 3D recontruction, Multi-view stereo, python and C++ development experience, multi-threaded coding.3D mesh registration, paraview and parameterizations. Moreover, I've deep understanding of data structures and algorithms. Experience with software development on Linux open-source stack. Calculus, linear algebra and geometry related courses have been taken.

M.Phil. in Electronics QAU, Pakistan

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONICS, QUAID-I-AZAM UNIVERSITY, ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- M.Phil. Supervisor: Prof Hasan Mahmood, Department of Electronics, QAU.
- Research: Signal and Image Processing
- Grade: A

M.Sc. in Electronics QAU, Pakistan

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONICS, QUAID-I-AZAM UNIVERSITY, ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN.

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

- 2nd position in batch
- Projects: completed 9+ projects related to C++, Verilog/HDL and Micro-controller programming.

B.Sc. in Mathematics and Physics

BZU. Pakistan

Bahauddin Zakariya University, Multan Pakistan

Mar. 2010 - Jun. 2012

• Grade: 1st Division

Presentation

IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems [IROS, 2020]

Las Vegas, USA

PRESENTOR AS AUTHOR

Oct. 2020

• Introduced Smart-Inspect for the micro scale localization and classification of smartphone glass defects for industrial automation.

Technology Start-up Support Scheme for Universities (TSSSU)

HKUST, Hong Kong

PRESENTER AS COO LISEE TECHNOLOGY CORPORATION COMPANY LIMITED, HONG KONG.

Jan. 2019

Introduced Lisee technology in front of selection committee panel and won TSSSU 2019-20 funding of the amount of HK\$300,000.

IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems [IEEE-CYBER 2018]

Tianjin, China

PRESENTOR AS AUTHOR

Jul. 2018

Introduced PCR-Pro for the estimation of information matrix and scale difference for pose graph SLAM.

IET-Young Professionals Exhibition and Competition (IET-YPEC) 2018

CityU, Hong Kong

Presenter as COO Lisee Technology Corporation Company Limited, Hong Kong.

Jul. 2018

• Introduced Lisee technology at IET-YPEC 2018.

Campus Challenge @ HKUST Transportation

HKUST, Hong Kong

PRESENTER AS PARTICIPENT

May 2018

HKUST got 80+ proposals for this compeitions, and arranged a roadshow. My proposal got selected for the audiance award after getting maximum votes.

High Tech Innovation and Entrepreneurship

PRESENTER AS ENTREPRENEUR

• Introduced my study related to the flying cars.

World First Youth Robotics Developemnt Forum 2017

Shangri-La Shenzhen, China.

Nov. 2017

Dec. 2017

HKUST, Hong Kong

Presenter as author.

- Introduced my work related to multi-agent SLAM system.

Honors & Awards _____

INTERNATIONAL

July, 2	Best Student Paper Finalist Award, IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and	Tianjin, China
July, 2	Intelligent Systems	riarijiri, Criiria
May, 2	2018 Audience Award, Campus Challenge - Transportation, HKUST	HKUST, HK
Nov, 2	2017 Best Mapper Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, China
May, 2	2017 Completion Award , The Graduate Teaching Assistant Training, HKUST	HKUST, HK
Dec, 2	2016 Best External Award, Robotics and Multi-Perception Lab, HKUST	Shenzhen, China
Nov, 2	2016 Completion Award , Author Workshop, Elsevier Publishing Campus	HKUST, HK

DOMESTIC

DOMEST	IC .	
Sep 2016	CCMS PhD Scholarship, Won Chief Minister Marit Scholarship (CCMS) scholarship award by Punjab Government (PEEF), Pakistan for pursuing my PhD studies at HKUST, HK	Lahore, PK
Sep 2013	Participant, Painting for peace (Pakistan-India-Afghanistan) event, a part of the Harmony initiative	Islamabad, PK
Apr 2013	Participant, Case Spark in business plan competition	Islamabad, PK
Apr 2013	Participant, Case EPICA	Islamabad, PK
Apr 2013	Participant, How to be a Better Playwright Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, PK
Oct 2012	Participant, Punjab Youth Festival	Lahore, PK
Oct 2011	Participant, Int'l Youth Conference and Festival	Islamabad, PK
Sep 2011	Participant, Asian Youth Conference and Peace Festival	Lahore, PK
Apr 2011	Completion Award , Acting and Directing Theater Workshop by PNCA and US Embassay Pakistan	Islamabad, PK
Dec 2011	Participant, National Drama Festival	Islamabad, PK
Dec 2010	Instuctor of short Course , PHP Web Development' at the Department of Electronics, QAU	Islamabad, PK
Apr 2013	Completion Award, Running River Rafting course by Adventure Foundation of Pakistan	Mansehra, PK
Apr 2013	Completion Award, Paragliding course by QAU Adventure Club	Islamabad, PK
Dec 2008	Award of Honor, Finance Secretary of Electronics Student Society (ESS) at QAU	Islamabad, PK

Academic Activities

icka Referee Service , ieee/RSJ international Conference on Robotics and Automation	2021, 2020
IROS Referee Service, IEEE/RSJ RA-L and International Conference on Robotics and Automation	2020, 2019, 2018
HKUST, HK Teaching Assistant , EESM 5547 - Multimedia Signal Processing	Spr 2020, Spr 2019,
TINOSI, TIN Teaching Assistant, ELSM 3347 - Multimedia Signal Processing	Spr 2018
CASE Referee Service, IEEE International Conference on Automation Science and Engineering	2019
HKUST, HK Teaching Assistant , ELEC4820 - Medical Imaging	Fall 2018
HKUST, HK Teaching Assistant , ELEC 1010 - Electronic and Information Technology	Spr 2017

Research Publications_

Why-So-Deep: Image Correspondence Verification by Probabilistic Spatial Landmarks Elevation for Visual Place Recognition

Journal Paper

M USMAN MAQBOOL BHUTTA*, LI TANG AND MING LIU

Submitted

The IEEE Transactions on Automation Science and Engineering(T-ASE)

Loop-box: Multi-Agent Direct SLAM Triggered by Single Loop Closure for Large Scale Mapping

Journal Paper

M Usman Maqbool Bhutta*, Manohar Kuse, Rui Fan, Yanan Liu and Ming Liu IEEE Transactions on Cybernetics (IF: 11+)

Oct 2020

3

Smart-Inspect: Micro Scale Localization and Classification of Smart Phone Glass Defects for Industrial Automation

Conference Paper

M USMAN MAQBOOL BHUTTA*, SHOAIB ASLAM, PENG YUN, JIANHAO JIAO AND MING LIU

IEEE/RSJ International Conference on Intelligent Robots and Systems (IROS 2020)

Conference Paper

Multiple Lane Detection Algorithm Based on Optimised Dense Disparity Map Estimation

comercineer aper

FAN

Han Ma, Yixin Ma, Jianhao Jiao, M Usman Maqbool Bhutta, Mohammud Junaid Bocus, Lujia Wang, Ming Liu and Rui

Dec 2018

Oct 2020

Accepted in IEEE International Conference on Imaging Systems and Techniques (IST 2018)

PCR-Pro: 3D Sparse and Different Scale Point Clouds Registration and Robust Estimation of Information Matrix For Pose Graph SLAM

Conference Paper

M USMAN MAQBOOL BHUTTA* AND MING LIU

Jul 2018

Presented in IEEE Int. Conf. on CYBER Technology in Automation, Control, and Intelligent Systems (IEEE-CYBER 2018), and won Best Student Paper Finalist Award.

An intelligent approach for robust detection and recognition of multiple color and font styles automobiles license plates: A feature-based algorithm

Conference Paper

M USMAN MAQBOOL BHUTTA*, HASAN MAHMOOD, AND HAROON MALIK

Jan 2015

Published in IEEE International Conference on Audio, Language and Image Processing (ICALIP 2014).

Efficient Reset Design Techniques

Journal Paper

QAMAR, ZOHA, BUSHRA YASEEN, AND USMAN MAQBOOL

arriar raper

Published in Science International Lahore

2015

Skills

Robotics and Computer Vision

Ubuntu, ROS, PCL, Docker, Catkin, Jupyter, Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, CUDA, OpenCV, OpenGV,

Ceres Solver, g2o, Libpointmatcher

Programming Python, C/C++, Matlab, git, LaTeX, FPGA, Verilog

Web mkdocs, Hugo, Jekyll, PHP, MYSQL

Languages English, Urdu

References

Prof Ming Liu

Ph.D. Supervisor

ASSOCIATE PROFESSOR · DIRECTOR OF ROBOTICS AND MULTI-PERCEPTION LAB (RAM-LAB), DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONIC AND COMPUTER ENGINNEERING, HKUST, HK.

eelium@ust.hk

(+852) 2358 7058

Dr. Cesar Dario Cadena Lerma

Exchange Co-Supervisor

Senior Researcher $\,\cdot\,$ ASL, ETH Zürich, Switzerland

cesarcadena.lerma@gmail.com

(+41) (0)44 633-8803

Prof. Hasan Mahmood

PROFESSOR · CHAIRPERSON, DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRONICS, QAU, ISLAMABAD, PAKISTAN.

M.Phil. Supervisor hasan@gau.edu.pk

(+92) (0)51 9064 3132